(綱手)うん 問題ない。
Okay. No problems.
よし！ 今日で退院だ。
All right, you can leave
the hospital today.
(カカシ)ひょっとして
そこのお荷物を➡
By any chance,
this isn't because
you want me to hurry up
早く持って行って
ほしいからじゃないですよね？
and take that baggage
with me, is it?
(ナルト)ガーッ…。
まぁ それもあるがな。
Well, there's that, too...
(サクラ)ナルトったら いつでも
修業が始められるようにって➡
That Naruto.
He refuses to leave
the hospital room
病室から離れなくって…。
so he can be ready to start training
at any moment...
ホントは 数日自宅でゴロゴロ… いえ
療養してからと思ってましたが➡
Truthfully, I was going to start
after kicking back.
I mean, recuperating
at home for a few days.
読む本も
なくなってしまいましたし…。
But I've run out of books to read...
チャッチャと修業やってしまいますか。
So I guess I'll just get right
to the training.
うん そうだな。
螺旋！
That's right...
Rasen!
ムニャムニャ…。
やった～ オイラの勝ち…。
All right! I win.
You have to treat me to
a year's worth of Ichiraku Ramen.
起きろ バカナルト！
Wake up, Idiot Naruto!
ブサイク… ん？
Ugly...
Huh?!
しゃ～んなろ～！
サクラちゃん！
Sakura...
Wind
さて 修業だ。
エヘヘヘッ…。
Okay, time for some training.
何だ？
What is it?
いやさ なんか
カカシ先生との修業って久しぶりで➡
Well, it's been a long time
since I've trained with you...
何でか よくわかんねんだけど
嬉しいんだってばよ！
I don't really know why,
but I'm glad...
I see.
そうか。
エヘヘヘッ…。
(カカシ)アハハハッ…
笑ってられんのも今のうちだぞ。
Laugh it up while you can.
えっ？
時間は待っちゃくれないからな。
Time won't wait for us, so...
病院でも言ったが
今回の修業の目的は➡
As I told you at the hospital,
the purpose of this training is
to create a Ninjutsu
お前だけの
最強忍術をつくることにある。
of ultimate power just for you.
螺旋丸を超える術だ。
A Jutsu that will exceed
the Rasengan.
それには チャクラの性質変化と➡
Two techniques,
"Change in Chakra Nature"
形態変化の
２つのテクニックが不可欠だ。
and "Change in Chakra Form,"
are crucial for that...
形態変化と 性質の変化？
Change in Chakra Form
and Change in...Chakra Nature?
ん？ ハイハイ。
一度に２つはわかんないね。
Okay, okay. You can't understand
two things at once.
I was wrong.
Sorry about that.
先生 悪かった ごめんごめん。
いや～ アハハハッ…。
じゃあ まずは
形態変化の説明からいこう。
Then, first let's go with the explanation
of Change in Chakra Form.
オッス！
(カカシ)螺旋丸をつくってみろ。
Right!
Try making a Rasengan.
あっ？ いいってばよ！
Huh?
Sure.
いくぜ！
おう！
Let's go!
Right!
螺旋丸！
Rasengan!
はい ストップ！
えっ？
Okay, stop!
お前はもう チャクラの
形態変化は マスターしている。
You've already mastered
the Change in Chakra Form.
えっ？
その螺旋丸がそうだ。
Your Rasengan has done that.
R-Rasengan...
螺旋丸…。
チャクラを
超スピードで乱回転させて 圧縮する。
Spinning Chakra like mad at
a super-high speed
and then compressing it...
このこと自体が
チャクラの形態変化であり➡
This in itself is
the Change in Chakra Form
and the Rasengan is a Jutsu
that has carried that to the extreme.
螺旋丸は それを極めた術だ。
Then that means I've passed
the Change in Chakra Form?
じゃあ 形態変化は合格ってこと？
そういうこと。
Yeah, that's about the size of it.
アハハハッ… ヤッホイ！
Yahoo!
はい 次はチャクラの性質変化だ。
Okay, next is
the Change in Chakra Nature.
うん うん！
Right, right...
そうだな 例えば千鳥。
Let's see...
Take Chidori for example...
この術は チャクラの形態変化と➡
This is a Jutsu activated
by simultaneously creating
性質変化 ２つの変化を同時に
起こして発動させる術だが…。
both the Change in Chakra Nature
and Change in Chakra Form...
見てろ。
右手にチャクラを集中させる…。
Watch this. I concentrate
Chakra in my right hand...
このチャクラを電流に性質変化させる。
I shift the property of this Chakra
into electrical current.
So this is the Change in Chakra Nature...
これが 性質変化？
That's right.
そうだ。 そして 今度は
放電するよう形態変化させて➡
And now I shift the form
so it will discharge electricity
and then I determine the range
and strength of the attack.
攻撃の威力と範囲を決める。
今までの螺旋丸以上の術を
習得するには 千鳥のように➡
In order to learn a Jutsu above
that of the Rasengan,
this combination of
the Change in Chakra Form
形態変化と性質変化
この２つの組み合わせが➡
and Change in Chakra Nature
絶対に必要となってくるわけだ。
is absolutely necessary,
like with the Chidori.
ヘヘヘ… じゃあ オレも 螺旋丸に
その性質変化ってのを加えたら➡
Then I'll be able to complete
a new Jutsu in a flash
if I add that Change in Chakra Nature
to my Rasengan!
あっという間に
新術完成しちまうってばよ！
ダハッ…。
あのね 簡単に言ってくれるなよ。
Listen.
That's easier said than done.
第一 まだ お前は 性質変化を
習得してもいないんだからね。
In the first place, you still haven't
even learned Change in Chakra Nature.
それに お前 自分が➡
And you don't even know
what Chakra Property you have, right?
どの性質を持っているかも
知らないだろう？
どの性質って？
Huh?! What Chakra Property?
ハァ… まぁ そこから
説明しなけりゃとは思ってたけど。
Well, I figured I'd have to start
explaining from there...
いいか？ 基本的に
チャクラの性質変化の種別は➡
Listen up.
Basically there are only five types
of Chakra Properties.
５種類しかない。 火 風 水
雷 土の５種類だ。
The five types are fire, wind,
water, lightning and earth.
そもそも この基本性質は
忍び五大国の名の由来でもあり➡
These basic properties are the basis
for the names of
the "Five Great Nations"
すべての忍術の基礎だ。
and they're also the foundations
of all Ninjutsu.
ふ～ん… そうだったのか。
No kidding. Really...?
だいたい みな どれかの性質に
当てはまるチャクラを持っている。
Everyone generally has Chakra
that falls under one of these properties.
例えば うちは一族なら
火の性質を持つ一族で➡
For example, the Uchiha clan
has the property of fire,
火遁の術を得意としている。
and Fire Style Jutsu
is their strength.
風なら風遁。 雷なら雷遁。
例えば 千鳥は雷遁の術の一種だ。
Wind has the Wind Style.
And lightning has the Lightning Style.
Chidori is one type
of Lightning Style Jutsu.
てことは サスケは 火と雷の
２つの性質を持ってるってことか。
So that means Sasuke has
the two properties of fire
and lightning, huh...?
で お前は 現在ゼロ。
しかも どの性質変化が➡
And you currently don't have any.
Moreover, we don't know what type
of Chakra Property you're good at.
得意なタイプなのかも
まだ わからない。
なに？
What's that?
それを この紙切れで調べる。
I'll find that out with
this strip of paper.
どうやって？
How're you going to do that...?
雷の性質なら 紙にシワが入る。
The paper gets wrinkled
if it's a lightning property.
風なら切れる。
It'll get cut if it's wind.
火なら燃える。
It'll burn if it's fire.
水なら濡れる。
It'll get wet if it's water.
土なら崩れる。
It'll crumble if it's earth.
これは チャクラに
反応しやすい感応紙で➡
This is litmus paper that reacts
easily to Chakra.
チャクラを吸って育つ
特別な木から作られる。
It's made from a special tree
that grows while absorbing Chakra.
この紙に自分のチャクラを流し込めば
自分が どの性質かがわかる。
If you flow your Chakra
into this paper,
you'll find out
what property you have.
よ～し…。
All right...
フッ…！
フンッ！
お前のチャクラの性質は 風だ。
Your Chakra property is wind.
風…。
Wind...
あらゆるものを
切り裂き 断ち切る。
It tears and cuts through
all sorts of things.
戦闘力抜群のチャクラだ。
It's Chakra with
outstanding battle strength.
おぉ～っ！ オレってば スゲエ！
Ooh! I'm awesome!
いや まだまだ
わかっただけだから…。
No, you've still only just figured
out your property...
さて いよいよ 風の性質変化を
身につける修業だが…。
Now at last,
we've come to the training
for learning the Change
in Chakra Nature for wind...
オッス！
Right!
However, it will take an enormous
amount of time to learn that technique.
しかし そのテクニックを会得するには
膨大な時間がかかる。
で その時間を
大幅に短縮する方法を➡
And so I hit upon a way to
drastically reduce that time.
オレが思いついてしまった
というわけだな。
スゲエ！
で その方法は…。
Awesome!
And the way to do that is...
ヤマト隊長！
Captain Yamato!
あれ？ どうして？ どうして？
Huh? Why, why?
(ヤマト)この修業は
ボクも協力するよう➡
Kakashi asked me to help out
with this training.
カカシさんに頼まれたんだ。
すみません カカシ先輩。
話の腰を折って。
I'm sorry for interrupting you,
Kakashi Senpai...
いやいや… でだな…。
あのさ… あのさぁ！
No problem...
- And you see...
- Hey! Hey!
ヤマト隊長の木遁てば
どの性質変化になんの？
What type of Change in Chakra Nature
is your Wood Style, Captain Yamato?
(ヤマト)えっ？ それは…。
Huh?
Well...
まぁ アイツの興味が
そっちに移っちゃったから➡
Well, his interest has
shifted that way,
so just go ahead and tell him.
パッと教えてやってよ。
はぁ…。
Uh-huh...
じゃ…。
Then...
土遁 土流城壁！
Earth Style: Rampart of Flowing Soil
うわっ！ なんだ…？
Whoa! What?!
水遁 滝壺の術！
Water Style: Waterfall Basin Jutsu!
滝ができた…。
He made a waterfall...
I have two Chakra Properties,
earth and water.
ボクは 土と水の
２つの性質変化を持ってるんだよ。
えっ!? じゃ
ヤマト隊長も２つ 持ってるの？
What?! You have two of them,
Captain Yamato?!
上忍クラスになると 皆 だいたい
２つ以上は持ってる。
Jonin-class Ninja generally
have two or more.
オレも 雷以外にも扱えるしな。
I've also got properties other
than lightning that I can use.
そんじゃ ヤマト隊長は 木遁も含めて
３つ 持ってるのか？
Then, Captain Yamato has
three properties
including the Wood Style?
いや そうじゃないんだな これが。
ん!?
No, that isn't how it works.
Huh?
ボクは 土と水の２つしか使えない。
I can only use earth and water.
そもそも 木なんていう
基本性質はないんだよ。
There is no fundamental property
known as "wood" to begin with.
Then how do you do it?
じゃ どうやって？
同時にやるんだ。
He does it simultaneously.
土と水の ２つの性質変化を
同時に行い➡
He does the Change in Chakra Nature
for earth and water at the same time
木の性質を 新たに発生させる。
and generates the new wood property.
(ヤマト)右手に 土。 左手に 水。
Earth with my right hand...
and water with my left hand.
すげぇ…。
That's awesome...
２つの性質変化を持ってる場合➡
If you have two Chakra Properties...
それぞれを 独立して使うのは
たいして難しくない。
it's not that difficult to use
each one independently.
But when it comes to generating
(ヤマト)だけど ２つの性質変化を➡
two Change in Chakra Natures
at the same time...
同時に発生させるとなると
話は別。
it's a different story...
２つの性質変化を同時に扱い➡
The power to generate a
new Chakra Property
by using two Change in Chakra Natures
simultaneously
新たな性質変化を生み出す力を
血継限界っていうんだよ。
is called the Kekkei Genkai.
You've at least heard of
that expression, haven't you?
その言い方くらいは
聞いたこと あるだろ？
うん。
Yeah...
かつて 戦った
白という少年もそうだ。
That boy you once fought
named Haku used it
He was able to use the Kekkei Genkai
known as the Ice Style...
彼は 氷遁という
血継限界を使えたんだが➡
But he generated "ice" by using
風と水の ２つの性質変化を
同時に用いて 氷を発生させた。
the two Change in Chakra Natures
of wind and water at the same time.
あれは 血継限界を持つ一族だから
できる 特別な術だ。
It's a special Jutsu
only those from a clan possessing
the Kekkei Genkai can use.
あの白も…。
Haku, too, huh...?
(カカシ)だから オレの写輪眼でも
コピーできなかったんだ。
So I couldn't copy it even with
my Sharingan...
No kidding...
ふ～ん…。
それじゃあさ シカマルの影真似とか
チョウジの倍化の術は どうなるの？
Then what about Shikamaru's
Shadow Possession Jutsu
or Choji's Expansion Jutsu?
それにさ 医療忍術とか幻術は
どうなっちまうの？
And what about Medical Ninjutsu
and Genjutsu?
う～ん… その説明には
また 時間がかかるし➡
Hmm, an explanation of that stuff
would take a while
and you'll just get confused
if I tell you all at once...
一度に話すと混乱するからな。
カカシ先輩！
Kakashi Senpai...
Why don't you save the yin and yang of
Change in Chakra Nature for another time?
(ヤマト)陰と陽の性質変化については
また 今度にしたら どうです？
Yin? And Yang?
What's that?
陰？ 陽？ なんだってば？
そうだな。 今 言っても
どうせ お前にはわからん。
Right.
You wouldn't understand even
if I told you now.
さて どこまで話したっけな？
Now, what were we talking about again?
えっ!? あぁ… なんか
修業の時間をズルしまくる方法って。
Oh... Something about how
to totally cheat on training time...
Reduce the time.
短縮する だ。
それ それ！ で… どうやって？
Yeah, that.
So, how do we do that?
それはな…。
Well, you see...
(カカシ)それはな…。
うん うん！
Yeah? Yeah?
多重影分身だ。
は…？
Multiple Shadow Clones.
Huh?
いや だから
多重影分身なんだよ 実は。
As it happens, it's all about
Multiple Shadow Clones.
何が…？
What about them?
It's how we reduce the training period.
だから 修業期間を
短縮する方法だよ。
ん～ん… 全然
わかんないってばよ。
Hmm...I don't get it at all.
はぁ… じゃ これから
説明するけど ちゃんと聞けよ。
Okay, I'll explain now, so listen up.
おっす！ なるべく
簡単に お願いするっす！
Right. Please keep it
as simple as possible!
(カカシ)はいはい…。
Okay, okay.
いいか？
Listen up...
Regular Clones
影分身の術が
ただの分身と違って➡
実体そのものを作り出す
忍術だってのは知ってるな？
the Shadow Clone Jutsu is a Ninjutsu
Shadow Clones
ああ もちろん知ってるってばよ！
ま 自分のコピー人間を
生み出す忍術だともいえる。
Well, you can also call it a Ninjutsu
for creating a copy of yourself.
I know because I can also use
the Shadow Clone Jutsu,
オレも お前ほどじゃないが➡
影分身の術を使えるから
わかるんだが➡
though not to your extent.
この術には 術者に及ぼす
ある特別な効果がある。
There is a particular effect this
Jutsu has on the caster.
お前も いつも使ってるから
え？
気づいているとは思うが…。
And since you're always using it,
I'm sure you've picked up on this...
影分身の分身体が
経験したことは➡
Anything experienced by
the Shadow Clone
術が解け 術者である
オリジナル１人に戻ったとき➡
is also experienced by the caster
その術者の経験として蓄積される。
after the clone has returned
to the caster's body.
I told you to keep it simple.
簡単にって言ったじゃん！
I knew you hadn't picked up on it.
やっぱ気づいてなかったのね。
I mean, I have no idea
what you're talking about.
…っつうかさ 言ってる意味
１つもわかんねえってばよ！
はぁ… なら２人で
とにかく影分身をやってみるぞ。
Then let's both try
creating Shadow Clones.
あ １体でいいからな。
へい！
Oh, one clone will be enough.
Right.
(２人)影分身の術！
Shadow Clone Jutsu!
よし じゃあ オリジナル側と
影分身側の二組にわかれて。
All right! Now let's split up into caster
and Shadow Clone teams...
The Shadow Clone team will
hide in the woods over there.
影分身の組は
向こうの林の中に隠れる。
影分身のナルトは ついてこい。
よっしゃ～！
Come with me,
Shadow Clone Naruto.
Right!
林の中の オレたち影分身組の姿は
オリジナルのほうからは見えない。
The originals can't see us,
the Shadow Clone team,
here in the woods.
そこでだ オレたちのほうだけ
ジャンケンをするぞ。
And now only we,
will play rock-paper-scissors.
What for?
なんで？
いいから ほら！
Just do it.
Hold it.
ああ 待って！
It won't be any fun if we just play
ordinary rock-paper-scissors.
ただ ジャンケンするだけじゃ
おもしろくないってばよ！
It's not supposed to be fun.
(カカシ)おもしろくなくても…。
Then the one who loses has
to treat the other to Ichiraku Ramen.
じゃあさ 負けたほうがさ
一楽ラーメン おごりね！
Okay, fine.
ああ わかったから！
やったぜ！
Yes! Now I'm fired up!
気合い入るってばよ！
(２人)ジャンケン…！
One, two...
影分身のほうは
何してんだってばよ？
What're the Shadow Clones doing?
もうすぐわかる。
You'll find out soon.
やり～っ！ 勝った！
Yes!
I won! You have to treat me,
Kakashi Sensei!
カカシ先生のおごりだってばよ！
はいはい。
Okay, okay. Now we're going to
break the Jutsu and vanish.
じゃあ オレたち影分身は
術を解いて消えるぞ。
Right.
おっす…！
ヘヘヘ…！
ヤツらは何をしていた？
What were they doing?
一楽ラーメン カカシ先生の
おごりだってばよ！
You have to treat me to Ichiraku Ramen,
Kakashi Sensei!
ジャンケンに勝ったからね！
I beat you at rock-paper-scissors!
勝手に約束しやがって…。
これで わかっただろ？
What're you doing arbitrarily
making promises like that?
Now you get it, right?
影分身の経験値は
オリジナルの中に蓄積されていく。
Shadow Clone experiences
are accumulated
within the original caster's body.
なるほど… 今まで
なんとなく影分身してたから➡
I get it...
I never realized it at all
because I was just sort of using
全然 気がつかなかったってばよ。
the Shadow Clones
without really thinking about it.
本来 この術は
危険な場所への偵察や➡
Normally, this Jutsu is used for
scouting dangerous locations
敵アジトに潜入して 情報収集に
使う術でもあるからな。
and gathering information by infiltrating
an enemy hideout, you see.
う～ん でも
それが わかったからって➡
But even having figured that out,
修業期間の短縮と
どう関係があるんだってばよ？
what does it have to do with
reducing the training period?
はいはい これから説明するって。
ヘヘ… やり～っ！
Okay, okay.
I'm going to explain that now...
Yes!
自来也様 螺旋丸なんて術を➡
Master Jiraiya sure did a good job of
teaching the Rasengan Jutsu to this kid...
よく この子に
教え込めたもんだよ まったく。
I'll say.
早く… 早く！
Hurry! Hurry!
つまり 影分身を使って
同じ修業を ２人で行えば➡
Basically, if you use a Shadow Clone
and conduct the same training
with two people,
the experience will simply
be doubled, right?
経験値は 単純に➡
２倍ってことになるだろう？
うん うん。
Right. Right.
To put it a different way, it also means,
if you use two people,
言い換えると ２人でやれば➡
１人で 修業するときに
かかる時間を➡
it'll take half the time it takes
to train alone.
半分に短縮できるって
ことでもある。
それが ３人なら ３分の１。
And it'll take one-third
the time if you use three.
３人なら ３分の１… あ！
One-third with three.
1,000人なら 1,000分の１だ。
One-thousandth with a thousand.
そっか！
I see...
つまり
１人で ２日かかる修業は➡
In other words, training that would
take two days alone
will take one day with two people.
２人なら １日でできてしまうし➡
１人で 20年かかる修業でも
1,000人なら 約１週間でいい。
Even training that would take
twenty years alone
will take around a week with
a thousand people.
That's awesome!
So we can do it that way!
すっげぇ！
そんな手があったのか！
《ようやく わかってくれたのね》
He finally got it, huh...?
You'll conduct
the Change in Chakra Nature training,
(カカシ)これから 習得する
チャクラの性質変化の修業は➡
you're going to learn now,
常に 多重影分身を使って行う。
オッス！
using the Multiple Shadow Clones
at all times.
Right!
エッヘヘ カカシ先生が強い理由
わかったってばよ！
Now I know why you're so strong,
Kakashi Sensei!
このやり方で
いっつも修業してたんだな？
So this is
how you did your training, huh?
No, I've never even once
trained using this approach.
いいや オレは
一度も こんなやり方で➡
修業したことは ない。
え？ なんで？
Huh?! Why not?
You can also make
Shadow Clones, can't you?
だって カカシ先生も
影分身できるじゃん！
確かにな…。
Indeed I can...
But I don't have as much
Chakra as you do.
だが オレは お前ほど
チャクラを多く持っていないし➡
And I can't sustain
my Shadow Clones as long, either.
影分身の持続時間も 短い。
なんせ チャクラを
均等に分散してしまう術だけに➡
And the only types
of Jutsu suitable for me,
チャクラの少ない オレには
不向きな術だからな…。
since I don't have much Chakra,
are the ones requiring an
even distribution of Chakra.
そうなの？ オレってば➡
Really? I have more Chakra than you,
Kakashi Sensei?
カカシ先生より チャクラ量が多いの？
オレの 約４倍だ。
You've got around four times
more than me.
Huh?! I've got that much?!
I'm pretty awesome, aren't I?!
え!? そんなに!?
オレってば 結構すげぇんだな！
九尾のチャクラを 抑えなければ
約100倍だ。
If you didn't suppress the power
of the Nine-Tails Chakra,
you'd have around
a hundred times more.
九尾の チャクラ…。
The Nine-Tails Cha
(ヤマト)だから これは キミにしか
できない修業方法なんだよ。
あ…。
(ヤマト)だけど➡
多くのチャクラを必要とするため➡
九尾のチャクラを 呼び起こしてしまう
可能性がある。
そこで ボクが呼ばれたんだ。
九尾のチャクラを
コントロールするためにね。
((サクラを傷つけたのは…
キミだよ。 ナルト))
頼むってばよ！
(カカシ)よし まずは
チャクラの性質変化が➡
より強くなるように 訓練する。
おう！
木の葉を 手のひらにはさんで
チャクラだけで切る。
真っ二つになるまでな。
よ～し やるぞ！
(カカシ)さっきも言ったが
この修業は➡
常に影分身で
やってもらう。
で… 何人くらいに
分身すればいいの？
う～ん…。
まっ １人 木の葉１枚として…。
あれぐらいかな。
(２人)ん？
なっ …ヘヘヘ。
影分身の術！
ん！
《もう 切れ目が入ったか…。
こりゃ案外 早いかもな…》